Dryden P. Morse papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Dryden P. Morse papers
1942-1999
Ms Coll 58
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1.25
3 boxes
Dryden P. Morse was a heart surgeon who practiced in Philadelphia and then at Deborah Heart and Lung Center in New Jersey. A pioneer in the use of pacemakers, he was an expert on the technology of pacemakers and invented several improvements. The collection contains a small amount of correspondence, published articles and unpublished manuscripts, and information on his inventions and his interactions with pacemaker companies.
Morse, Dryden P. (Dryden Phelps), 1924-2002
Biographical / Historical
Dryden Phelps Morse, a heart surgeon and pioneer in the development and use of pacemakers, was born in Berkeley, California in 1924. During his childhood, he lived in China for two years with his mother and stepfather. He attended Harvard College from 1941 to 1943 and then entered military service in World War II. He received his M.D. from Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons in 1947. Morse did most of his residency training in Philadelphia. His thoracic surgery residency was at Hahnemann Hospital and at the Bailey Thoracic Clinic under pioneer heart surgeon Charles P. Bailey. Morse served in the American Medical Corps in the Korean War, 1952-1954. From 1962 to 1972 he was Chairman of the Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery at Albert Einstein Medical Center, Northern Division, in Philadelphia. From 1961 to his retirement in 1991 he was associated with Deborah Hospital in Browns Mills, N.J., as an attending physician. From 1979 on, he served as Director of the Pacemaker Clinic, and full-time attending surgeon, Thoracic Surgical Service, at Deborah. Morse published extensively including a book on heart surgery (1963) and three editions of a guide to pacemakers. He was an expert on the technology of pacemakers and invented several improvements such as the Morse-Edwards Horseshoe annuloplasty ring, and a telephone pacer monitoring system with Ted Stern. Morse was a founding member of the North American Society for Pacing and Electrophysiology in 1979, now the Heart Rhythm Society. At least twice he was invited to lecture in China.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains biographical materials; some correspondence; publications, both reprints and unpublished articles; materials on Morse's inventions related to cardiac pacemakers and on his relations to companies manufacturing pacemakers; and specifications of pacemakers gathered for Morse's publications.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Tom Morse, son of Dryden P. Morse, 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research except for a few folders containing patient health information. For these, contact the Librarian for Medical History.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: 1. General. 2. Correspondence. 3. Presentations at conferences. 4. Writings. 5. Additional materials on pacemakers and other medical inventions. 6. Additional photographs.
Cardiac pacemakers; Cardiac pacemakers -- Complications; Cardiac pacemaker industry; Coronary heart disease; Defibrillators; Heart -- Diseases; Heart -- Surgery; Heart valves -- Surgery; Medical instruments and apparatus; Mitral Valve -- Stenosis; Correspondence; Floppy disks; Photographs; Reprints; Thoracic surgeons -- New Jersey; Inventors; Bailey, Charles P. (Charles Philamore), 1910-1993; Blanco, Gumersindo, 1922-2007; Gessman, Lawrence J.; Nichols, H. T. (Henry Thomas), 1920-; Parsonnet, Victor, 1924-; Albert Einstein Medical Center; Cordis Corporation; Deborah Heart and Lung Center; Droege Computing Services, Inc; Hahnemann Medical College and Hospital of Philadelphia; Heart Rhytym Society; MEDphone Corporation; Medtronic, Inc; Gessman, Lawrence J.
- General, Series I
  - Curriculum Vitae, ca. 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Several copies. In the latest version, Morse removed his Deborah Hospital address and left his home address. There are no publications listed after 1988, although Morse did have later publicatons.
  - Copy of birth certificate (1924), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Harvard College and application for war service, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains drafts in Morse's hand on his activities at Harvard that prepared him for war service. Folder also contains letters of recommendation and an information form for the U.S. Naval Reserves.
  - Army service: World War II and Korean War, 1946-1954, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Official forms of army service.
  - Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, Class of 1947, "Newsletter and Directory", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Medical registration: New York, Pennsylvania, New Jersey, 1955-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Appointments" and memberships, 1956-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    These files, organized by Morse under "Appointments," contain appointments to various hospital staffs, appointments to universities, election to membership in various professional organizations, and appointments to committees. Salaries were marked over or cut out prior to the donation of the papers.
  - "Appointments" and memberships, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of Fellows taught, 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Last names have been written on four cards stapled to a sheet of paper.
  - Biographical information on Dryden P. Morse (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes a student paper on Dryden Morse based on interviews, 1997, and a biography/obituary downloaded by the archivist from the website of the Heart Rhythm Society, May 1, 2017.
  - Materials referring to Dryden P. Morse (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, Series II
  - Deborah Hospital: News, correspondence, etc., 1974-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Newsletter of Deborah Hospital; a two-page publication introducing Deborah Hospital; an invitation to "The Deborah Symposium on Congenital Heart Disease," lists of committees; Morse's nomination and appointment as chief of surgery in 1984: typescript, "The Use of Programmable Pacemakers at Deborah"; draft of a promotional article, "Deborah," by Morse; and correspondence on Morse's retirement in 1991.
  - Deborah Hospital medical staff conferences (Restricted), 1961, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    These mimeographed documents include names, addresses, and conditions of patients (including a risk percentage) who were approved or not approved for heart surgery. The second document includes summaries of cases of named patients and their treatment thus far. The cases were to be presented at the next conference to determine if surgery was indicated.
  - Dedication of expansion of Deborah Heart and Lung Center by President Gerald Ford, 1981 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes remarks of Gerald Ford, a news release, a copy of a newspaper clipping, and a photograph of Ford and others at a meal.
  - Correspondence on the "Morse Ring", 1962-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Morse states in his Curriculum Vitae that he was the developer of the first valve annuloplasty ring, the Morse-Edwards Horseshoe annuloplasty ring, in 1963. (Morse had labelled the folder "Morse Ring".) It was developed in connection with the Edwards Laboratories, Inc., Santa Ana. California. Folder contains results of animal experiments, a photograph, and also information on the Carpentier-Edwards Flexible Support Mounted Xenograph.
  - Correspondence: Symposium on Anesthesia for Cardiac Surgery, organized by Morse, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    The symposium was scheduled for May 6, 1964 to be held at the Albert Einstein Medical Center, Philadelphia. Correspondence concerns invitations to possible participants and their responses.
  - Letter from the Chinese Medical Association rejecting Morse's proposed visit to China, 1966 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    This interesting political letter by Fu I-chen, Vice General Secretary, notes with approval Morse's opposition to the Vietnam War, but, because of U.S.-China relations, "we find the time for such a visit is not ripe under present extreme abnormal relations between China and U.S." Morse had lived in China for two years as a child.
  - Correspondence: Charles P. Bailey, 1966, 1975, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Some of the correspondence is about an invitation to Deborah to talk about "Early Cardiac Surgery at Deborah" in 1989. Bailey, Morse's mentor, had been associated with Deborah Hospital in the early years of cardiac surgery there.
  - Correspondence on programmable pacemakers (Restricted), 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Contains patients' names, especially patients whose pacemakers had been replaced by an Omnicor or Stanicor model by Cordis Corporation. Includes two drafts of abstracts in which Morse was an author.
  - Correspondence: Shanghai Pacemaker Lecture Tour, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Correspondence with Chinese physicians. The lectures were preceded by a meeting of the Cordis Corporation.
  - Shanghai Pacemaker Lecture Tour, other materials, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    The China trip took place May 11-21, 1982. Folder contains abstracts of presentations by Morse, Victor Parsonnet, and others; lists of names of Chinese people whom Morse met; a list of cardiologists and thoracic surgeons in China; Morse's printed account, "China Trip," from an unidentified newsletter; three slides and a photograph with captions; and a photocopy of Cordis Corporation leaflet in English and Chinese.
  - Proposed visit to China, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Morse and his wife Terry planned to visit the affiliated hospital of Suzhou Medical College after the Cordis Pacing Seminar in Shanghai.
  - Correspondence on the telephone defibrillator in collaboration with MEDphone, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Folder includes a grant proosal to Deborah Hospital describing the project; correspondence; testing protocols; abstracts for presentations; minutes of meetings; a news release; and photocopies of newspaper clippings. Morse was one of several physicians involved with this project.
  - Correspondence: Victor Parsonnet, Newark Beth Israel Medical Center, 1999 and no date (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Concerns the North American Society of Pacing and Electrophysiology. Also contains genealogical information on the Parsonnet family.
- Presentations at conferences, Series III
  - Abstracts for presentations at conferences, 1961-1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rejected abstract: Dryden Morse, et al, "The Use of the Demand Pacer: Three Years Experience in 140 Patients", 1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Folder contains the typescript abstract by Dryden Morse, Leonard Dreifus, Gumersindo Blanco, Alberto Adam, and Henry T. Nichols, all authors from the Hahnemann Medical School and Hospital, as well as a letter from William D. Williams, American College of Cardiology, rejecting the abstract for the program.
  - Sariel G. G. Ablaza et al, "Aortic Valve Replacements by a Calf Heterograph:Two years Follow-up in the Human," presented at the American College of Cardiology, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Authors are Sariel G. G. Ablaza, Henry T. Nichols, Gumersindo Blanco, Harry Goldberg, and Dryden Morse. Folder contains a carbon copy of the abstract, a handwritten draft, and an announcement of the conference.
  - Dryden Morse, et al., "Bleeding Coagulation Problems in Open Heart Surgery," for the "Thoracic Surgery Forum", no date (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Writings, Series IV
  - Reprints and photocopies of published articles, 1951-1991; Subseries 1
    This set of articles is incomplete. In his CV, Morse listed 133 articles published from 1951 to 1988.
    - Articles, 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Articles, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Articles, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Articles, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Articles, 1980-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Unpublished manuscripts, Subseries 2
    Manuscripts labeled as unpublished and manuscripts that do not appear by title in Morse's CV.
    - Victor P. Satinsky and Dryden P. Morse, "Correction of Intrathoracic Tracheal and Cardiac Compression Due to Irremedial Causes," unpublished, ca. 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Charles P. Bailey, et al, "An Advanced Approach to the Problem of Mitral Stenosis", ca. 1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Authors are Charles P. Bailey, Houck E. Bolton, and Dryden P. Morse.
    - Charles P. Bailey, et al., "The Direct Relief of Pulmonary Stenosis in the Closed Technique: Review and Analysis of 168 Cases, ca. 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Authors are Charles P. Bailey, Henry T. Nichols, Teruo Hirose, and Dryden P. Morse.
    - Dryden P, Morse et al, "Open Heart Surgery and Blood Coagulation Defects", ca. 1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Authors are Morse, -- Gollus, William Weise, Edward Ehrlick, Alex Ulin, and Charles P. Bailey, all from the Hahnemann Hospital, the Bailey Thoracic Clinic, and the Blood Coagulation Laboratory of the Cardiovascular Institute. This was a mimeographed "first draft."
    - Dryden P. Morse, et al, "The Results of Various Procedures in Coronary Artery Disease", ca. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Authors are Dryden P. Morse, Nelson F. Moury, William Likoff, and Charles P. Bailey.
    - Dryden P. Morse, "Mitral Stenosis", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Several versions of a manuscript eventually "submitted to the Einstein Journal, 1961." "From the Department of Thoracic Surgery, Albert Einstein Medical Center, Philadelphia." It was not published in this form.
    - Alan V. Newhoff et al, "Pulmonary Embolectomy Utilizing Total Cardiopulmonary Bypass: Report of Successful Operative Case", ca. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Authors were Alan Y. Newhoff, Henry T. Nichols, and Dryden P. Morse. A later version of the paper was published with two cases. See CV, article 44.
    - H. T. Nichols et al., "A New Type of Coronary Catheter for Use in Open Heart Surgery", ca. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Authors are H.T. Nichols, D.P. Morse, G. Blanco, S.G. Ablazo, and A. Hehle. 1966 is the latest date mentioned in the paper.
    - "Cataracts and Contacts", 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Unpublished manuscript written for a popular audience. The manuscript describes Morse's own cataract operation at Wills Eye Hospital in Philadelphia.
    - "Bilateral Incisions for Open Heart Surgery, Introduction, dictated by Dr. Morse", no date (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Dryden Morse and Henry T. Nichols, "Pacemakers: Indications for Use and Treatment", no date (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - D.F. Downing and Charles P. Bailey, "Errors in the Treatment of Tetralogy of Fallot by Closed Method (Brock Procedure), no date (1950s) (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Case studies of Bailey's operations in which the patient died. There are no patient names.
  - Books, Subseries 3
    - The Pacemaker and Valve Identification Guide (1978): Prosthetic heart valve photographs, ca. 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Folder contains a draft of a letter on Deborah Hospital letterhead, March 4, 1976, to companies that manufacture prosthetic heart valves, requesting photographs and technical descriptions for a guide to prosthetic cardiac valves. Folder also contains many unidentified photographs of synthetic heart valves, a few of them labeled Deborah Hospital on the back. The book was authored by Dryden Morse and Robert M. Steiner and published by the Medical Examination Publishing Company, Garden City, NY.
    - Specifications of pacemakers by the American Pacemaker Corporation (Woburn, Mass.), 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Correspondence, brochures, and specifications. Some of the information was used in Dryden Morse and Robert M. Steiner, The Pacemaker and Valve Identification Guide (Garden City, NY: Medical Examination Publishing Co., 1978).
    - Specifications of pacemakers for an update of A Guide to Cardiac Pacemakers, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      The update appeared as Dryden Morse, Robert Steiner, and Victor Parsonnet, A Guide to Cardiac Pacemakers (Philadelphia: F.A. Davis Co., 1983). Folder also contains a brochure advertising the book.
    - Specifications of pacemakers by Arco Company/Intermedics, Inc. (Restricted), 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Specifications for three Arco models as requested by Morse for inclusion in A Guide to Cardiac Pacemakers (1983). Folder contains one computer printout of names of patients who were implanted with specific models of pacemakers, the date of implantation, and information on replacement models. There is also a photograph of an Arco pacemaker.
    - Correspondence with pacemaker companies and information on models, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      This information was probably collected for the Guide to Cardiac Pacemakers published in 1983. Folder contains photographs of pacemakers, negatives, and leaflets from foreign companies.
    - A Guide to Cardiac Pacemakers (1991): Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      This book was an update of three previous guides to cardiac pacemakers. Dyden P. Morse, Victor Parsonnet, and Lawrence J. Gessman, A Guide to Cardiac Pacemakers (Durham, NC: Droege Computing Services, 1991). It was sold in both book and database formats.
    - A Guide to Cardiac Pacemakers (1991): Correspondence with Droege Computing Services (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - A Guide to Cardiac Pacemakers (1991): Database information (Box 3, Folder 4)
      The pacemaker information was organized by means of a database through Droege Computing Services, Durham, North Carolina. Folder contains a 5 1/4 inch floppy disk and a user's manual. One could purchase a bound book, a binder with tabs, or the computer database.
    - Outline of a proposed book on heart disease for lay people (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Additional materials on pacemakers and other medical inventions, Series V
  - Instruments designed by Charles P. Bailey and Morse: Catalogs of the George Pilling and Son Co., 1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Two instrument catalogs of George P. Pilling and Son, Philadelphia, for cardiac-thoracic and vascular instruments that include instruments invented by Charles P. Bailey, Morse's mentor, and/or Morse.
  - Gumersindo Blanco, "Coating and Implantation of a Right Ventricular Outflow Patch Prosthesis," research proposal, no date (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Gumersindo Blanco was a colleague and co-author of Morse. The proposal is addressed to the New Jersey Heart Association c/o Dr. Dryden P. Morse.
  - "New Concepts in Pacing", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    It is not clear who wrote this typed piece. It points out several current problems with the effectiveness of pacemakers and presents ideas of how to attack them. Following the proposal are several appendices, numbered and annotated by Morse.
  - Biotronik Cardiac Pacemakers, ca. 1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Brochure on "Milestones in Biotronik's History."
  - Cardiac Control Systems (Palm Coast, Florida), Investment Information (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Detailed information on the company, what it manufactures, and about its finances.
  - Cordis Corporation (Restricted), 1969, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Folder restricted because of patient information. "Technical Memorandum P-6" on replacement of pacers; lengthy summary of the Cordis Corporation meeting in September 1981, at which Morse spoke. A letter of Morse to Dr. Stan Saulsen contains EKG strips of a named patient who had been given a Sequicor II pacer. Morse makes a suggestion for improvement of the pacemaker settings.
  - MEDphone Corporation (Paramus, N.J.), Medical Advisory Board, 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Contains material on the Medical Advisory Board, on stock options, a copy of a newspaper article, and a news release about an agreement with Mount Sinai Hospital to offer "MDphone." See also Box 1, Folder 23.
  - Medtronic, Inc. (Minneapolis): Brochures and specifications for the "Chardack" implantable pacemaker, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Medtronic, Inc., Physician Review Board, 1988-1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Medtronic, Inc., Rate-Responsive Advisory Panel, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Medtronic, Inc.: Publications on the history of electrotherapy, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Additional photographs, Series VI
  - Photographs by the Ocean County Bureau of Public Relations, Toms River, NJ, no date (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Two copies of a photograph of seven men, one of whom may be Dryden Morse.
  - Photographs for publication, group 1, no date (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Photographs of a chest X-ray, instruments, and drawings. These materials were found separate from the next group.
  - Photographs for publication, group 2, no date (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Photographs of drawings and of a chest X-ray.
  - Photograph of President Lyndon B. Johnson promoting the "Heart Fund.", ca. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Lyndon Johnson opened the Heart Fund Campaign of The American Heart Association on February 7, 1965. He proclaimed February as American Heart Month. The folder contains a staged photograph of Johnson holding a heart design surrounded by six little girls in dresses with hearts on them and with sashes with the words "Heart Fund." Photograph by Harris & Ewing, Washington, D.C. On the back is written "Old Frontispiece" and "Please do not use this."